<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0" xml:id="ch_documentation">
    <title>Documenting your Pepper module</title>
    <para> One of the most important but often forgotten tasks when creating a Pepper module is to
        document the behavior of it and its functionalities. Therefore the sample project contains a
        template for creating a documentation. The documentation in SaltNPepper in general is done
        in DocBook (see: <link xlink:href="docbook.org/">docbook.org/</link>). DocBook is a
        documentation language written in XML and enables to transform the documentation into
        several target formats like html, pdf, odt, doc etc.. <note>
            <para>We recommend to use the template, for a uniform view to all Pepper modules. That
                makes it possible not to forget important issues to be mentioned and makes it easier
                for the user to have a good understanding of what the Pepper module is doing.</para>
        </note> You will find the template in
            <filename>SAMPLE_HOME/src/main/docbkx/manual.xml</filename> among other
        directories containing files necessary for the transformation. To refer to images from the
        manual, put them into the image folder
            <filename>SAMPLE_HOME/src/main/docbkx/images/</filename> and make a relative
        reference the xml file. </para>
    <sect1>
        <title>Transformation</title>
        <para>The standard transformation configured for the sample project is producing the formats
            html and pdf. The configuration is done in the <filename>pom.xml</filename> of the
            project. To add further output formats, just copy the respective
            plugins to your pom and change them.</para>
        <para>When executing the maven goal site <synopsis>mvn clean site</synopsis>maven will
            create a manual folder under <filename>SAMPLE_HOME/target/manual</filename>,
            where you can find the pdf and the html documentation.</para>
        <note>
            <para>The current configuration does not need to be changed, just write your
                documentation by overriding the template. The rest will work automatically. In some
                cases it might be necessary to adapt the transformation, then please take a look to
                the xsl transformation files in
                <filename>SAMPLE_HOME/src/main/docbkx/docbook-xsl/</filename>.</para>
        </note>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
