<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Pepper</title>
        <subtitle>Developer's Guide for PepperModules</subtitle>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Florian</firstname>
                    <surname>Zipser</surname>
                </personname>
                <email>saltnpepper@lists.hu-berlin.de</email>
            </author>
            <author>
                <orgname xml:id="org1">INRIA</orgname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <orgname xml:id="org2">SFB 632 Information Structure / D1 Linguistic
                    Database</orgname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <orgname xml:id="org3">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <orgname xml:id="org4">Universität Potsdam</orgname>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        <copyright>
            <year>2012</year>
            <holder><xref linkend="org1"/>, <xref linkend="org2"/>, <xref linkend="org3"/>, <xref
                    linkend="org1"/>,<xref linkend="org4"/>, All rights reserved.</holder>
        </copyright>
        <releaseinfo>Version ${project.version}</releaseinfo>
    </info>
    <preface>
        <title>Foreword</title>
        <para>The aim of this document is to provide a helpful guide to create own PepperModules to
            plug them into the pepper framework. Currently this document is not in a very good state
            so far. It is not more than a loose collection of hopefully interesting information for
            developers. But we are working on it, to fullfill its aim and to make a helpfull and
            readable guide out of it. </para>
        <para>We are trying to make things as easy to use as possible, but we are a non profit
            project and we need your help. So please tell us if things are to difficult and help us
            improving the framework. </para>
        <para>You are even very welcome to help us improving this documentation by reporting bugs,
            requests for more information or by writing sections. Please write an email to
                <email>saltnpepper@lists.hu-berlin.de</email>. Have fun developing with
            SaltNPepper!</para>
    </preface>

    <chapter xml:id="ch_intro">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Since Pepper is a plugable framework, we used an underlying framework called OSGi
            (see: <link xlink:href="http://www.osgi.org/">http://www.osgi.org/</link>) providing
            such a functiuonality. OSGi is a mighty framework and has a lot of impact in the way of
            programming things in java. Because we do not want to force you to learn OSGi, when you
            just want to create a new module for pepper, we tried to hide the OSGi layer as good as
            possible. Therefore and for the lifecycle management of such projects, we used another
            framework called maven (see: <link xlink:href="http://maven.apache.org/"
                >http://maven.apache.org/</link>). Maven is configured via an xml file called
            pom.xml, you will find it in all SaltNPepper projects and also in the root of the
            SampleModule project. Maven makes things easier for use especially in dealing with
            dependencies. </para>
        <para>In the following, <xref linkend="ch_setUpEnv"/> explains how to set up your
            environment to start developing your pepper module. <xref linkend="ch_sampleModule"/>
            explains how to download and adopt a template module to your own needs. This module than
            is the base for your own module. In <xref linkend="ch_customization"/> we explain how to
            add properties to your module, so that the user can dynamically customize the behaviour
            of the mapping. <xref linkend="ch_documentation"/> shows the usage of a documentation
            template written in doocbook (see <link xlink:href="http://www.docbook.org/"
                >http://www.docbook.org/</link>) to make a standard documentation for the user of
            your module. Since testing of software often is a pain in the back, the pepper-testSuite
            already comes with some predefined tests. These should save you some time, not to test
            even the simplest things. Last but not least, this documentation contains a FAQ. SInce a
            FAQ lives of questions, if you have some, just help us increasing that part and send a
            mail to <email>saltnpepper@lists.hu-berlin.de</email>.</para>
    </chapter>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="settingUpEnvironment.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="sampleModule.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="customization.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="documentation.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="testing.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="faq.xml"/>
</book>
